Did you…
你…
commit murder?
是否殺了人？
I'll ask again.
我再問你一次
Did you…
你是否…
commit murder?
殺了人？
Let me ask a different question.
容我換個問題
What do you think it means
你覺得作為殺人犯活著
to live as a murderer?
代表著什麼？
"Killer." "You don't deserve to live."
“殺人凶手”、“你不配活著”
"Scum." "Pay for your crime with death."
“人間敗類”、“給我以死償命”
The moment they convict you,
一旦判定有罪
those words will rain down upon you.
這些狠毒的話便會刺向你
Strangers you've never met will pierce your heart as if it's nothing
素未謀面的陌生人 會用成千上萬把利刃
with tens of thousands of knives.
毫不在乎地將其插進你的心裡
And it won't just be directed at you.
這些利刃針對的不只有你一人
Your family, partner, friends, colleagues…
你的親人、伴侶、朋友、同事
Everyone who's been part of your life
與你的人生有過交集的每一個人
will be forced to wear the label of being associated with a murderer.
都將被迫貼上 “我和殺人犯有關係”的標籤
Innocent people will be treated as if they were criminals.
無辜之人也會遭受罪犯般的待遇
It might even be more cruel than serving time in jail as a murderer.
殺人犯還能在牢裡過活 他們的處境可能會更加悽慘
Of course, if you genuinely repent for your crime,
另一方面，若你真誠面對自己的罪行
and they consider you rehabilitated, you might be able to end your sentence.
法官也認定你改過自新 你當然能刑滿出獄
Legally speaking, that is.
我指的是法律層面的出獄
But it doesn't absolve you of your crime.
但並不代表著你已從罪行解脫了
Even if you've committed an offense, you can still start fresh.
犯了罪依然能重新做人
Do you believe that Japan is a forgiving country that allows for that?
日本這個國家十分寬容 你真心如此認為嗎？
Consider this.
你仔細想想
What if a murderer moved into a room next to yours?
假如有個殺人犯搬到你家隔壁呢？
If they confessed to you, "I've killed someone,"
當對方坦承“我殺過人”
could you nod and smile in response?
難道你還能笑著回對方“是喔”？
It's the same with rehabilitation centers for criminals.
罪犯的更生機構也不例外
Everyone acknowledges their importance to society,
世人皆知這在社會上是必不可少的
but no one desires to live near one.
但都不希望那種設施蓋在自家附近
That's human nature for you.
那就是人性
You understand now, don't you?
如今你明白了吧？
Even if you're forgiven within the confines of the law,
即使在名為法律的規則中得到了寬恕
in the real world,
回到現實世界
the public isn't about to forgive someone who's committed a crime.
世人仍不會原諒一度犯下罪行之人
No matter how much they've reformed,
無論你怎麼洗心革面
there's no place for them once they leave prison.
出了監獄後你依舊沒有歸宿
They can never find happiness.
罪犯永遠得不到幸福
Eventually, they succumb to despair, kill again, or end their own lives.
最終會在絕望之下再度殺人 或者自絕性命
It's the only future that awaits them.
那就是等著罪犯的未來
The instant you become a murderer, your life is over.
在成為殺人犯的那一刻 你的人生就毀了
It can't be helped. After all…
這也沒辦法，畢竟啊…
you've committed murder.
你奪走了別人的性命
Apologies.
恕我冒犯
Let's get back on track.
我們言歸正傳
Today, I've come to share something important with you.
我今天來到這裡 是為了向你告知一件重要消息
What you decide to do with this opportunity is up to you.
如何利用這個機會取決於你
I will ensure
我保證讓你
you receive an acquittal.
獲判無罪
Will we arrive on time?
趕得上嗎？
We're cutting it close.
時間快來不及了
But I can't go any faster.
但現在的速度是極限
Aren't you going too fast?
你不覺得開太快了嗎？
What's going on?
搞什麼？
Pull over after the traffic lights.
麻煩到那個紅綠燈後停車
For crying out loud!
倒楣透頂！
Open the window, please.
請開車門
You were going pretty fast. Please step out.
你超速了，方便下車嗎？
I'm so sorry.
真是不好意思
My passenger, he…
乘客在趕時間
How fast were you going?
你的時速是多少？
Here's my card.
這是我的名片
ATTORNEY MASAKI AKIZUMI
（明墨法律事務所 律師，明墨正樹）
For speeding, the protocol is to tail the vehicle for 100 meters,
如果遇到超速 按規定需跟車100公尺測速
assess their speed, and then activate the siren.
之後鳴笛，我說得沒錯吧？
At what speed were you pursuing us?
你跟車的距離是多少？
-Seventy kilometers. -I see.
-70公里 -是喔
Let's start here.
你看，從這裡開始
One, two, three, stop.
一、二、三，停
That's three seconds.
只有三秒鐘
To pursue us from that alley for 100 meters,
從那條小巷出發，跟車100公尺
you would have had to drive at 120 kilos.
你的時速必須達到120公里
I hate debating whether one did something or not,
我懶得跟人爭辯對方有做或沒做
so I've taken to recording videos for self-protection.
所以近來開始錄影自保
Also, if you want to crack down on drivers, don't lurk.
另外，如果要取締 我勸你最好不要躲起來
I suggest you patrol boldly in the middle of the road.
何不在道路中央正大光明地抓人？
Especially since the roads in Tokyo are dangerous.
東京都內的道路特別不安全
See?
看吧
Good day.
告辭
Good morning.
大家早
-Good morning.
-早安
I'm glad to see you seem so busy.
看你這麼忙，真替你開心啊
Thankfully, I believe I've finally caught up with your level, Mr. Himeno.
多虧有你，我現在已經 能夠和姬野檢座平起平坐了
You're being too modest.
你太謙虛了
But punctuality is crucial.
不過守時可是我們的規矩
Despite how it may seem, we're quite busy as well.
別看我們這樣，其實我們很忙的
Though perhaps not as busy as the hotshot lawyer.
不過還是比不上 你這位當代菁英律師就是了
Thank you.
多謝誇獎
I was able to get ready while you were lecturing me.
在你指責我的期間 我已經做好了準備
Shall we begin?
那我們開始吧
By the way…
順帶一提
I've also had to wait.
我也被迫等了好一陣子
You've invested much time in the interrogation.
訊問似乎花去各位不少時間
How many rearrests did you make?
你們重新逮捕嫌疑犯幾次了？
It's my policy to conduct thorough investigations.
深入調查是我的原則
Is that right?
這樣啊
Your Honor, since time is limited, shall we start?
主審法官，時間似乎不多了 我們開始吧
Indeed.
好的
As stated in the indictment, the victim is Asao Hanegi, aged 54,
正如起訴書所述 被害人是大田區一間名叫羽木精工的
the president of Hanegi Seiko, a small factory located in Ota Ward.
小工廠社長，54歲的羽木朝雄
The accused is Keita Hiyama, aged 35, an employee of the said factory.
被告同為該公司員工 是35歲的緋山啓太
He's accused of homicide under Article 199 of the Penal Code.
因觸犯刑法第199條被控殺人罪
On January 30th, 2024,
令和6年1月30日
around 9:45 p.m…
晚間9點45分左右
The victim was murdered at his residence adjacent to Hanegi Seiko.
被害人在和羽木精工廠房 相鄰的住家內遭人謀殺
VICTIM: ASAO HANEGI
（被害人，羽木朝雄）
According to Mr. Hitoshi Ogata, the first person on the scene,
尾形仁史先生是第一發現者 據他所言
Mr. Hiyama, the accused, was assigned overtime work that day.
被告的緋山先生當天接獲加班指示
Please, let me go home already.
拜託你，今天就讓我下班吧
Sure thing.
可以啊
Once you've finished what I asked, then you can leave.
把我剛才吩咐的做完就能回家
Don't make me repeat myself.
我說過好幾次了
Did your parents not teach you anything?
你爸媽怎麼教你的？
As he hid in the shadows, waiting for the argument to end…
他躲在陰影處等他們吵完…
You'd better clean that up.
給我收拾乾淨
I'll kill him.
我要殺了你
What now?
幹嘛？
You still have a problem?
你還有意見嗎？
That's the perspective of the prosecution.
這就是檢方對整起事件的觀點
But we're still uncertain about its accuracy.
但真實性有多高還不清楚
The motive seems to stem from your typical power harassment.
感覺殺人動機是常見的職權騷擾
They should enact laws recognizing self-defense in cases of harassment.
那政府就該針對職權騷擾 制定正當防衛的法條
It won't justify murder, though.
但殺人就是不對
Thirty-five years old,
35歲
no prior criminal record, a first-time offense…
沒有前科，初犯…
Mr. Akamine, is this your first time dealing with a homicide?
赤峰先生，你是頭一次處理殺人案？
Yes, it is.
對，是的
I've handled an assault case at my previous workplace,
我在上一間律師事務所 處理過暴力案件
but I'm new to lay judge trials.
但沒參與過陪審團審判
Well, you'll adjust soon enough.
沒關係，相信你不久後就能適應
By the way,
我順便問一下
what's the evidence linking Mr. Hiyama to the murder?
緋山先生動手殺人的證據是什麼？
Security camera footage showing the accused entering and leaving.
錄下被告出入的監視器影像
His fingerprints found at the crime scene.
現場找到的被告指紋
The accused's DNA found under the victim's fingernails.
被害人指甲間驗出的 被告DNA鑑定報告
And the testimony of Mr. Hitoshi Ogata,
還有公司同事尾形仁史先生
the accused's coworker who was first on the scene.
作為第一發現者的證詞
Based on these four, we will prove his guilt in court.
檢方將基於這四項證據 透過法律手段證明被告的罪行
Very well.
明白了
Anything from the defense counsel?
辯護人有沒有意見？
Allow me to confirm once more.
容我再確認一次
Is this all the evidence you've requested?
檢方請求的證據就這些？
It is.
沒別的了
Thank you.
感謝回答
Will the focus be on how to mitigate his sentence?
辯論重點在於 該如何爭取減輕被告的刑罰嗎？
Mr. Akamine, could you join Mr. Akizumi from now?
赤峰先生，你稍後可以 和明墨律師碰頭嗎？
Of course.
沒問題
You have arrived at your destination.
抵達目的地
This is the place.
就是這裡啊
You must be out of your mind!
你是瘋了嗎？
I have nothing to say. Leave!
我無可奉告，請你離開！
Wait, please! I beg you!
先別關門，拜託你！
Ms. Shinomiya, right?
你是紫之宮小姐，對嗎？
It's me, Akamine.
敝姓赤峰
Mr. Aoyama instructed me to come here.
我來是應青山先生的吩咐來的
Isn't it risky to visit the crime scene and meet the victim's family?
直接勘查現場或是上門見被害人家屬 不是很危險嗎？
We're not on their side, after all.
我們畢竟是對造的立場
Go home, then.
那你回家去吧
Raise your arm up to your shoulders. Good.
肩膀和手臂呈直線，就是這樣…
If you throw the ball now, you should get some good distance.
從這個位置投出去 應該可以投很遠，你試試
-Hey. -Hmm?
-跟你說喔 -嗯？
Did you know? Ueno Zoo got a new red panda called Sei.
上野動物園來了隻 叫做小聖的喜馬拉雅小熊貓
Minato,
小湊
remember not to talk to strangers.
不可以跟陌生人說話
And wasn't that at Tama Zoo?
而且小聖是多摩動物園的動物吧？
Was it?
是嗎？
Yup.
是呀
And Sei went abroad already.
而且牠到國外了
Oh…
這樣啊
Here, Minato. That was fun.
球給你，小湊，我玩得很開心
Let's play again.
下次再一起玩吧
-Yeah. Bye-bye! -Bye-bye.
-好，拜拜！ -拜拜
Let's go inside.
我們進屋去吧
Excuse me.
失陪了
Come on. Let's go.
來，這邊
How'd it go?
你查得怎麼樣？
Not good.
很抱歉
As expected.
想也知道不順利
Minato seems to be doing okay.
小湊看上去過得還不錯
That's a relief.
這下可以放心了
-Yeah. -Is Mommy home?
-是啊 -媽媽在家嗎？
That man back there is Mr. Ryo Sato, an employee.
剛才那個男人是廠內員工 佐藤涼先生
Is something bothering you?
你對他感到在意？
No, not yet.
不，還不算
Not yet?
還不算？
Starting today, I'm officially joining your team.
我從今天開始正式加入團隊
-I'm Aka-- -Akamine, how would you defend this case?
-敝姓赤峰… -你會怎麼替這件案子辯護？
Me, sir? Um…
你問我嗎？我看看…
Given the circumstances of the crime scene,
依現場情況來看
it seems clear that Hiyama committed the crime.
絕對是緋山先生所為
So I'd focus on his motive and mitigating--
應以犯罪動機作為辯護重點 尋求減刑…
Mr. Hiyama is pleading not guilty.
緋山先生主張自己無罪
True, but the prosecution has presented four pieces of evidence.
可是檢方提交的證據足足有四樣
That's quite a lot.
既然有這麼多證據…
Let me tell you something.
告訴你一件事
For us, the more evidence there is, the better.
對我們而言，證據是越多越好
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
Is Mr. Akizumi a masochist?
律師是超級被虐狂嗎？
Are you stupid?
你是笨蛋嗎？
The footage is from this camera.
影像就出自這台監視器
It shows Mr. Hiyama leaving the factory around 9:45 p.m.,
監視器拍到緋山先生 在疑似案發時間的
the time the crime allegedly occurred.
晚間9點45分前後離開工廠
However, this doesn't prove that Mr. Hiyama committed the murder.
但這並不能證明他殺了人
On the contrary…
那反過來想…
What would constitute strong evidence in this case?
這個案子裡的什麼東西 會成為強而有力的證據？
The murder weapon.
用於殺人的凶器
When he left, he wasn't wearing the jacket he had on when he arrived for work.
而且他離開時並未穿著 上班時穿的那件外套
Maybe he removed the jacket because it was stained with blood?
是因為濺上血跡而脫掉了？
It might be inside this bag,
他可能將外套放在這個袋子裡
or he might have disposed of it somewhere within the factory.
或是在工廠裡找個地方處理掉了
Locating either the weapon or the jacket would provide the prosecution
假如找到犯案凶器或那件外套
with an advantage in proving Mr. Hiyama's guilt.
對檢方十分有利
These two items were not among the evidence presented by the prosecution.
那兩樣都不在檢方提出的證據中
The fact that they deliberately submitted weak security camera footage…
他們反倒刻意提出了 佐證力度較弱的監視器影像…
It's like a hedgehog.
就像刺蝟
Huh?
什麼？
The prosecution lacks decisive evidence for this case.
檢方這次沒找到決定性的證據
So they're relying on camera footage,
因此他們結合了監視器
fingerprints, eyewitness testimony, and DNA.
指紋、目擊者證詞、DNA
They're trying to establish guilt with multiple pieces of evidence.
諸如此類的各種證據 試圖證明緋山有罪
Even a hedgehog without its thousands of spines is just a rodent.
倘若刺蝟沒了身上那千百根刺 不過是隻老鼠罷了
One spine alone is weak, which is why it defends itself with multiple spines.
單獨一根刺太過弱小 所以需要許多刺方能一戰
The more evidence, the better.
“證據是越多越好”
In other words, we just need to pluck the spines one by--
所以我們之後 要將檢方的刺一根根地…
Is that him?
就是他嗎？
Yes, he's Mr. Hitoshi Ogata, the first on the scene.
對，他是第一發現者的尾形仁史先生
You can't.
這麼做不明智
Engaging with the prosecution's witness can raise issues!
隨意接觸檢方的證人會惹出麻煩！
Akamine, take that off.
赤峰，取下你的律師徽章
Mr. Ogata.
尾形先生
You're Mr. Ogata, right?
你是尾形先生，沒錯吧？
Who the hell are you?
你是誰？
Sorry for interrupting your break. Could I have a moment?
抱歉打擾你休息
Apologies, Himeno couldn't make it today.
抱歉，今天姬野來不了
Himeno?
姬野？
Oh, the prosecutor.
哦，檢察官啊
We're here to hear more from you again.
我們今天又來問話了
He may seem pleasant, but he's quite the taskmaster.
別看他有張可愛的臉蛋 使喚人可沒在留情
But I've already told him everything.
可是我先前都跟他全盤托出了
Do you enjoy the races?
你喜歡賽馬啊？
Sort of.
是沒錯
I've been considering getting into them myself.
我最近也想開始接觸
Are they exciting?
真的好玩嗎？
Well, yeah.
是啊，還算好玩
Sorry, please let us double-check.
不好意思，我想再確認一次
Mr. Hiyama is claiming innocence.
緋山先生主張自己無罪
Are you aware of this?
你知道這件事嗎？
You only found the victim on the floor,
你單單發現了受害者倒在地上
and you didn't see the perpetrator.
並未目擊凶手的身影，對吧？
What led you to suspect Mr. Hiyama?
你怎麼會認定是緋山先生殺的人？
Why does it matter?
這有什麼關係？
I just need to follow your instructions, right?
我只需要照你們說的做不就行了？
You're not the one who actually killed him, are you?
總不會其實是你殺的吧？
What?
你說什麼？
You know how they always say in detective dramas,
刑偵劇裡經常提到一句話
suspect the first person on the scene?
“首先得懷疑第一發現者”
Did I get it right?
被我說中了嗎？
Absolutely not!
怎麼可能！
I returned to the factory to get my glasses around 9:40 p.m.
我大約在晚間9點40分回到工廠 取回我的眼鏡
Did your parents not teach you anything?
你爸媽怎麼教你的？
That's when I overheard Hiyama arguing with the boss.
當時我聽見緋山和社長起爭執
Then, I heard a scream from his house, so I hurried over there.
直到社長住家傳來慘叫聲 我才急忙衝過去
Boss!
社長！
What's going on?
怎麼回事？
Honey, what happened to you?
老公，你怎麼了？
-Talk to me! -Boss!
你說啊！
Then I witnessed the boss lying on the floor near the entrance,
趕到後我發現社長倒在玄關處
and I promptly called the police and ambulance.
於是急忙報警並叫救護車
Very good.
真不錯
Your account is quite precise.
你的陳述簡潔明瞭
You must have rehearsed it a lot.
看來練習過不少次
By the way,
順帶一提
the machine Mr. Hiyama was using…
緋山先生使用的機台
Which one is it?
在哪裡呢？
Huh?
啥？
That one?
是這台嗎？
Um, may I ask you something?
不好意思，可以請教你一個問題嗎？
When you were reading earlier,
我看你剛才看字時
you weren't wearing your glasses.
沒有戴眼鏡
Are you nearsighted?
你是近視嗎？
On the night of the incident,
你說在案發當晚
you headed home without your glasses, right?
忘了自己沒戴眼鏡就回去了？
That's why I went back to get my glasses!
所以我不是說了嗎？ 我回工廠來拿眼鏡！
Give me a break already.
你們少得寸進尺
I told you I'm showing up for the trial, okay?
都說了我一定會出庭
Sorry about that.
失禮了
Apologies for taking up your time.
抱歉在你百忙之中打擾
Why did you ask about his glasses earlier?
對了，你剛剛為何提起眼鏡這件事？
Huh?
什麼？
Well, I'm nearsighted as well.
其實啊，我也有近視
I can't step outside without my contacts.
沒戴隱形眼鏡會怕到不敢外出
So when he mentioned forgetting his glasses, it seemed odd.
所以他忘了戴眼鏡這件事 讓我覺得奇怪
-Sorry if I overstepped. -It's fine.
-抱歉，是我踰矩了 -沒關係
By the way, I couldn't confirm from the footage
還有一件事，我無法透過影像確認
whether Mr. Ogata was wearing glasses when he returned to the factory.
尾形先生回到工廠時是否戴了眼鏡
I see.
這樣啊
Um…
請問一下
they'd be furious if they found out we contacted their witness.
如果我們接觸檢方證人一事曝光 會不會遭受強烈譴責？
We even lied we were the prosecution.
況且我們還謊稱自己是檢方
There's no law against contacting the prosecution's witness.
法律不曾明定辯方不能接觸檢方證人
And we never claimed to be the prosecution in the first place.
再說我們本來就沒有 聲稱自己是檢察官
AKIZUMI LAW OFFICE
（明墨法律事務所）
Mr. Akizumi, you have evidence that Mr. Hiyama is innocent, right?
所以說律師手上握有 緋山先生不是凶手的鐵證？
Um, I mean…
那個，我是說…
Given the false accusation case six months ago,
你要怎麼比照半年前的那樁冤案
I'm curious how you'll get an acquittal for Mr. Hiyama.
讓緋山先生獲判無罪？
I don't have any evidence.
我手上沒有鐵證
Does that mean we're actually trying to help a murderer, then?
那我們是真的要幫殺人犯脫罪？
A murderer?
殺人犯？
Tell me, Akamine,
赤峰
why do you believe Mr. Hiyama committed murder?
你覺得緋山先生為何要殺人？
Because…
那是因為…
he suffered severe power harassment.
他遭受了嚴重的職權騷擾
That's why he killed?
所以他憤而殺人？
An attorney's duty
律師身為保護者
is to defend the legitimate interests of their client, the accused.
必須維護客戶，也就是被告的利益
Regardless of how heinous the crime,
即便凶手再殘忍
until convicted, they should be treated as innocent and protected.
在判決有罪前，律師都應視其無罪 並維護他們的權益
Any attorney who presumes Mr. Hiyama's guilt at this stage
現階段就認定緋山先生是凶手的律師
should resign immediately.
最好立刻辭職
Anyway, whether he actually committed a crime or not
何況他真的犯罪與否
is not our concern as attorneys.
都不是我們律師該煩心的
But if we're unsure about a client's guilt,
但如果不清楚客戶是否犯了罪
how can we protect them?
我們也沒辦法幫助他們吧？
You crush it.
那就摧毀啊
It's the prosecution's job to gather evidence and establish guilt.
檢方的職責是準備證據 證明被告有罪
And our role, as attorneys,
至於我們律師的職責
is to take the evidence presented by the prosecution…
就只要將檢方提出的證據…
and crush it in our hands.
予以摧毀就行了
The race has started.
比賽開始了
Dammit! He got a late start!
可惡！起跑就落後！
Damn…
（投注券）
Come on…
不會吧…
Go!
快跑…
Pass him!
超過去！
What the hell? Dammit!
搞什麼？混帳！
Dammit.
真是該死
I delved into Mr. Ogata's background.
我去查了尾形先生的背景
He's been changing jobs quite frequently.
發現他經常換工作
Whoa, that's a whole lot.
哇，這麼多啊
There must be a reason he can't hold down a job.
感覺一定有什麼原因讓他做不久
A reason?
做不久的原因？
Mr. Ogata only repeated what was written in the statement.
尾形先生只復述了供述書上的內容
The prosecution has coached him well.
依我看他極大程度受到了檢方操控
I witnessed the boss lying on the floor near the entrance,
我發現社長倒在玄關處
and I promptly called the police and ambulance.
於是急忙報警並叫救護車
Like reciting a script?
又不是在唸台詞
Is it normal for the prosecution to micromanage their witnesses?
檢方會控制證人到那種程度？
Maybe they didn't want their witness to speak freely for some reason.
可能是因為不限制證人言論 會惹出什麼問題吧
It's inconvenient for the prosecution that Mr. Ogata was the first on the scene.
尾形先生是第一發現者，對檢方不利
So they coordinated the narrative and scripted a testimony.
因此雙方統一口徑 捏造出了類似劇本台詞的證詞
This might be related to why he's constantly changing jobs.
而這點或許和他經常換工作有關
Maybe we should tail him a little.
我們應該追查他一陣子
And it falls on me to tail him.
結果追查的任務落在我身上
Oops.
糟糕
Regarding his motive,
關於殺人動機
Mr. Hiyama has admitted to experiencing power harassment.
緋山先生承認自己遭受職權騷擾
Although it's not strong evidence,
雖說佐證力度薄弱
the security camera also shows
但監視器顯示
that Mr. Hiyama was present in the factory at the time of the victim's death.
於受害者的判定死亡時間 緋山先生人在工廠內
If it's true that Mr. Hiyama's DNA was found on the body,
若遺體檢測出了 緋山先生DNA一事無誤
all that remains is…
剩下的就只有…
I'm back.
我回來了
The fingerprints.
指紋
Correct.
沒錯
Mr. Hiyama's fingerprints were found on the inside of this door and this shelf.
在這扇門的內側以及架子上 驗出了緋山先生的指紋
Could they have been left before the incident occurred,
我認為這些指紋可能不是案發當天
The prosecution claims these fingerprints were left on the day of the incident.
檢方提到這些指紋 是在案發當天留下的
However, they haven't substantiated that they were indeed left on that day.
但他們無法證實是否真是如此
Fingerprints indoors can persist for up to two months.
若是留在室內的指紋 經過兩個月通常還能驗出來
Sounds too convenient…
那種說法也太牽強了
Sorry.
抱歉
Welcome back.
歡迎回來
Keep going, Ms. Shinomiya.
你可以繼續說，紫之宮小姐
In 2019,
令和元年
there was a case where the accused faced charges of burglary and murder.
有一樁案例 被告因強盜殺人嫌疑遭到起訴
But they couldn't verify if the prints were left on the day of the crime,
但檢方無法證明謀殺現場的指紋 是否為當天留下的
resulting in an acquittal.
因而無罪釋放
The prosecution is operating under the assumption
檢方以緋山先生有罪為前提行動
They've cleverly woven together the evidence they've collected
他們將到手的證據巧妙串聯
and crafted a narrative that aligns with their agenda.
捏造出對他們有利的敘述
In that case, our task is simply to reshape the narrative
既然如此 我們只需要改寫他們的敘述
So that's what he meant by crushing the evidence.
摧毀證據就是那個意思啊
But to achieve that, we'll need to prove
可是如此一來，我們就得證明
that Mr. Hiyama was inside Mr. Hanegi's house before the incident.
緋山先生在案發前 就進過了羽木社長家
I have nothing to say. Leave!
我無可奉告，請你離開！
Wait, please! I beg you!
先別關門，拜託你！
That day, is that why…
她當時是為了…
I think we still have options to explore.
我覺得還有方法
PUBLIC PROSECUTORS OFFICE
（檢察廳）
Good morning.
早安
-Good morning.
-早安
So, how did the defense counsel react?
然後辯方的反應怎麼樣？
Despite the abundance of evidence we presented, they remained unfazed.
我們找到這麼大量的證據 對方仍舊不動聲色
They even seemed to expect more evidence from us.
不僅如此 似乎還期待我們提出更多證據
That's attorney Akizumi for you.
明墨律師就是那樣的人
I've heard
我聽說他們
they're requesting the victim's family as witnesses for the upcoming trial.
要求被害人家屬 以證人身分出席下一次公審
It's outrageous.
腦子壞掉了吧
They'll exploit even the victim's family to secure their desired verdict.
為了審判，甚至不惜利用被害人家屬
They're despicable.
簡直是人間敗類
And what's your take?
所以穩妥嗎？
Her husband was murdered.
自己的丈夫可是遭人殺害了
I've never heard of the bereaved testifying on behalf of the accused.
我從沒聽過被害人家屬 為被告出庭作證這種事
I even gave her a warning, just in case.
而且為了以防出意外 我還特意叮囑了那位夫人
-I'm impressed. -But Ms. Midorikawa.
-果真周全 -不過綠川檢座
Why did that man appoint himself to defend Hiyama?
那個男人怎麼會自願為緋山辯護？
He must be confident he can secure an acquittal.
想必是有信心讓他脫罪吧
There's concrete evidence against him.
但我們有確鑿的證據證明他有罪
If it were that easy to get an acquittal for a murderer,
要是簡簡單單就能讓殺人犯無罪
this country would be hopeless.
這個國家就完了
I'm back.
我回來了
Well, I'm calling it a day.
那我先下班囉
See you.
辛苦了
How did it go?
情況如何？
Did Mr. Hanegi's wife talk to you?
你跟羽木太太說上話了嗎？
I got you a pastry
我買了麵包回來
if you want it.
你要吃嗎？
If you're hungry…
餓不餓…
No, thank you.
不必了
Okay.
好
I'll have it, then.
那我要吃
Go ahead.
請用
Don't worry.
不用多想
Shinomiya's always like that with newcomers.
小紫對剛認識的人都是那樣子
Got it.
了解
I've emailed you the details regarding the mass food poisoning.
關於集體食物中毒事件的處理文件 我把資料寄到你信箱了
Thank you.
謝謝你
But I suppose this matter takes precedence.
不過這案子比食物中毒案更嚴峻
It's a tough one, isn't it?
不好搞定，對吧？
This household never invited their employees inside?
社長家平時 從不放員工進去的，不是嗎？
That's right.
對
But I'll try to speak with Mr. Hanegi's wife again.
但我想再次嘗試接觸社長夫人
Only two more days until the trial. Good luck!
離庭審還剩兩天，加油
Yum.
好吃耶
Anko sweet bean paste and cheese.
裡面包的是紅豆和起司
COURTHOUSE
（法院）
Good day.
辛苦了
Um, Ms. Shinomiya isn't here yet.
那個，紫之宮小姐還沒到
Good luck.
加油
Thank you.
還請多關照
Mr. Akizumi.
明墨律師
Are you trying to stage a performance for the lay judges?
你是打算在法官面前作秀嗎？
You want the victim's wife to testify for the accused.
竟敢要求被害人的妻子做被告證人
I highly doubt she'll show up, though.
想也知道她不會出席
Mr. Himeno.
姬野檢座
Let's do our best.
我們彼此都盡力而為吧
All rise.
全體起立
THE FIRST PUBLIC TRIAL
（第一次公審）
The court is now in session.
我們即刻開庭
I will address the accused.
我想問問被告
On the day of the incident,
案發當天
you pursued the victim who had returned home from the adjacent factory.
你追著想回到工廠旁住家的被害人
You subsequently struck the victim's head with a blunt object.
隨後以形似鈍器之物重擊被害人頭部
You are denying this accusation.
你否認了此項指控，沒錯吧？
Yes.
沒錯
I didn't kill him.
我沒殺他
I'll proceed with my questions.
那我繼續提問
What were you doing around 9:45 p.m.?
當天晚間9點45分左右 你在做什麼？
Mr. Hanegi instructed me to keep working,
羽木社長吩咐我繼續作業
so I was cutting and shaving metal parts.
所以我當時正對著 金屬零件進行切割加工
Can anyone corroborate this?
是否有人能證明？
No.
沒有
In order to refresh his memory,
為幫助他喚起記憶
I'd like to present evidence number 7 as requested by the prosecution.
我方申請出示檢方請求證據 甲字第7號
May I?
庭上是否同意？
You may proceed.
可以，請便
This is camera footage from the day of the incident.
這是案發當天的監視器影像
It shows you arriving at the factory and leaving in a hurry.
上頭顯示了你上班時 以及急匆匆離開時的畫面
Do you notice anything?
有發現哪裡不同嗎？
That's right.
沒錯
On your way out, you're not wearing the jacket you had on when you arrived.
你下班時並未穿著上班時的那件外套
So, where did that jacket go?
既然如此，那件外套到哪去了？
Is it inside this bag?
在袋子裡嗎？
I don't know.
我不知道
When you killed the victim, his blood got on your jacket,
外套在你殺人時沾上了受害者的血
so you disposed of it along with the weapon. Am I wrong?
所以你將其和凶器一起處理掉了 我有說錯嗎？
Objection!
有異議！
That question unfairly assumes the accused is guilty.
檢方認定了被害人有罪 這個問題並不妥當
Prosecutor, what is your stance?
檢察官是什麼看法？
I believe it's acceptable to pose questions based on logical assumptions.
我認為根據合理推斷 提出的問題是可接受的
Objection sustained.
反對成立
Prosecutor, please inquire about the facts based on the evidence.
檢察官應憑證據詢問事實真相
Apologies.
非常抱歉
You endured verbal abuse from the victim on a daily basis,
據說你日日忍受被害人口中 像是“笨蛋”
I have statements from other employees corroborating this.
其他員工也證實了這一點
You were experiencing power harassment.
意即你受到了職權騷擾
And on that day, your pent-up frustration reached its breaking point.
而案發當天你積怨難消，於是爆發
I'd never take a life for such a reason.
我不會因為那種理由動手殺人
Then why were your fingerprints found at the murder scene?
那你的指紋為何會留在凶案現場？
Apart from the victim's family,
除了受害者家屬以外
only your prints were discovered in the home.
室內只驗出了你的指紋
Additionally, DNA from your skin was found under the victim's nails.
而被害人指甲內也驗出了 你的皮膚碎屑，即DNA
Isn't this because you had a tussle with the victim on that day?
這難道不是你 當天和被害人爭執時留下的？
We'll move on to the defense counsel's interrogation based on their evidence.
接下來開始驗證辯方請求的證據
First, the victim's family, whom they requested as witnesses…
首先有請辯方申請出庭作證的 被害人家屬
What now, Mr. Akizumi?
律師，怎麼辦？
Defense counsel?
辯護人？
Your Honor, we will examine the witness we have previously requested.
庭上，我方這就對 先前請求出庭的證人進行詢問
Here is our witness.
證人已到
The witness is Minato Hanegi, the son of the victim.
證人為被害人兒子，名叫羽木湊
He's five years old.
這男孩今年五歲
Wait a moment.
慢著
How could you put such a young child on the stand?
怎麼能讓如此幼小的孩童 站上證人席？
He's the victim's family!
他可是被害人遺屬！
He's present with his mother's consent.
我方已取得母親的許可
This is outrageous!
怎麼可能！
He's a witness listed in the evidence request.
這位證人正式列入了 請求驗證的證據列表上
HARUKO HANEGI MINATO HANEGI
（證人 羽木春子，羽木湊）
Minato, can you share with everyone here what you told me earlier?
小湊，你能在這裡說出 剛剛和姐姐說過的話嗎？
Yeah.
可以
Thanks.
謝謝你
What's your favorite game?
小湊喜歡玩什麼？
Ball.
玩球
You enjoy playing ball?
你喜歡玩球啊？
Where do you play?
你都在哪裡玩？
In front of my house.
我家門口或其他地方
With your friends from kindergarten?
跟幼稚園的好朋友一起玩？
No, with a young mister.
不，我都跟哥哥玩
A young mister?
哥哥？
Who is this young mister?
這個哥哥是誰？
Is he here?
他在這裡嗎？
That man.
就是那個哥哥
The man you pointed to,
你剛剛指的是
is he the one seated next to the men dressed like police officers?
坐在像警察的人旁邊的那個男人嗎？
-Yeah. -Your Honor!
-對 -庭上！
I believe the defense counsel guided the witness to point to the accused.
我認為辯方誘導證人指向被告
Is that so?
真是如此嗎？
It didn't appear that way to me.
在我看來不像誘導
Defense counsel, please proceed.
辯護人，請你繼續
Thank you.
好的
Minato,
小湊
do you often play ball with the man you pointed to?
你跟你剛才指出來的哥哥 經常一起玩球？
Yeah. He fetched my ball for me.
對，他會幫我撿球
He fetched your ball?
幫你撿球？
Where was the ball?
他幫你撿哪裡的球？
Behind the doggie.
小狗上面的球
To clarify his statement, I'd like to present a photograph,
為釐清證人說法，我方在此請求
evidence number 32, as requested by the defense counsel.
出示辯方請求證據第32號的照片
You may proceed.
請便
You said the ball was behind the doggie.
你說的“小狗上面”
Do you mean this white doggie in the photo?
是這張照片裡的白色小狗嗎？
Yeah.
對
Your ball ended up behind the doggie,
扔到小狗上頭的球
and that man helped you retrieve it?
是這個哥哥幫你撿回來的，對吧？
Yeah. I couldn't reach it even if I tried.
對，因為我伸直手也勾不到
Thanks.
謝謝你
The prosecution's evidence shows they found the accused's prints here too.
根據檢方請求證據 此處同樣驗出了被告的指紋
And Minato's testimony suggests
依小湊的證詞，被告人他呢
the accused would've been inside their home prior to the incident.
在案發前就曾進入被害人家中
Can you get that ball behind the doggie for me?
幫我拿丟到那隻小狗上面的球
Found it.
找到了
Here you go.
拿去
Thanks.
謝謝
In other words, the prints the prosecution presented as evidence
也就是說，檢方提出的指紋證據
can be traced back to before the incident happened.
可以視為案發當日前所留下的
The witness is just five years old.
證人年僅五歲
Children's memories can be vague.
幼童的記憶模糊不清
His testimony isn't reliable!
可信度不足以佐證！
True. It's normal to doubt what a young child says.
一個孩子所說的話 確實有可能不太可信
Mister!
哥哥！
I find it hard to believe the witness is lying.
但我不認為證人在撒謊
Article 143 of the Code of Criminal Procedure states,
刑事訴訟法第143條規定
"The court may, except as otherwise provided in this Code,
“若本條無特殊規定 法院得以請任何對象
examine any person as a witness."
作為證人進行詰問”
That was a legitimate testimony.
剛才那番話即為合法證詞
It is up to all of you to determine its credibility.
判斷其是否具有可信度則取決於各位
That is all.
我方詰問結束
See? There's Mommy.
你看，媽媽來了
Minato!
小湊！
-Were you okay? -Yeah.
-你還好嗎？ -嗯
Thank goodness.
太好了
-Bye-bye! -Bye-bye.
-拜拜！ -拜拜
I'll see you out.
我送兩位出去
Let's go, Minato.
我們走，小湊
I'm amazed you got Minato to testify.
沒想到你會找小湊作證
You're incredible, Ms. Shinomiya.
紫之宮小姐，你真行
I'll never testify for you.
我死也不會幫你們作證
I don't recall ever allowing that man into our house.
再說我根本不記得 自己讓那個男人進過我家
My husband was murdered!
我先生被人殺害了！
I'll call the police if you keep harassing me.
如果你再繼續糾纏，我會報警！
I have LEGO sets of a zoo.
我有動物園的樂高積木
And ANIA toys too!
還有多美動物模型喔！
Yeah?
是喔
Excuse me.
叨擾了
Minato said he wanted to show me his toys.
小湊說要讓我看他的玩具
Stay away from my son.
離我兒子遠一點
He might receive the death penalty.
那個人可能被判死刑
We don't believe Mr. Hiyama is the culprit.
我們不認為緋山先生是凶手
Minato testified
小湊作證說
that he let Mr. Hiyama inside the house before the incident occurred.
他在案發前讓緋山先生進入家中
This testimony will be absolutely pivotal in the case.
他的說法會是本案最重要的證詞
Minato, go inside.
小湊，你先進去
I heard that Mr. Hanegi's relationship with Mr. Hiyama
我聽說羽木社長和緋山先生的關係
took a sudden turn for the worse in the last six months.
在近半年來急遽惡化
Do you know what caused it?
夫人是否知道原因？
No.
我不知道
Well, there's a rumor going around that you were attracted to Mr. Hiyama.
好吧，有謠言指出 你對緋山先生有好感
That's ridiculous.
實在太荒謬了
Hiyama, did you get a haircut?
緋山，你剪頭髮了？
You're looking even more handsome.
看起來又更帥了
I just…
我只是…
gave him a simple compliment about his appearance.
誇了他很帥而已
You can't assume I was attracted to him.
那就叫有好感？
Let's consider a hypothetical scenario.
我只是做個假設而已
Even if it was just a joke and you didn't intend anything by it,
假如這只是說笑 若你確實沒有別的企圖
what if Mr. Hanegi overheard your words?
一旦那句話傳進羽木社長耳裡
What if his misunderstanding led to the deterioration of their relationship
讓他擅自往壞處想，使他倆關係惡化
and played a role in this incident?
此事多多少少導致本案發生呢？
We're not asking you to lie on our behalf.
我們不是要你撒謊
I believe it is true you never let Mr. Hiyama inside your home.
你不曾讓緋山先生進入自家是事實
However, Minato told us clearly that he let Mr. Hiyama inside.
但小湊明確告訴我 他讓緋山先生進了家門
If we don't clarify this in court,
若不在法庭上坦承此事
Mr. Hiyama will be convicted,
緋山先生會被判有罪
and he'd have to live the rest of his life as a murderer.
必須以殺人犯的身分度過終生
There's a precedent for this.
有這麼一個案例
A person was arrested for murder and sentenced to death.
某人被視作殺人犯逮捕 獲判死刑定讞
They spent over ten years in prison,
過了十多年的牢獄生活
waiting for their execution day.
如今仍在等待執行死刑的那一天
But what if they were innocent all along?
但如果他其實無罪呢？
They lost their family,
他失去了親人
and endured life inside a dark, cold, grim cell,
窩在陰暗冰冷、毫無生氣的牢房裡
simply waiting for death.
一天天等待死亡來臨
Strangely, the evidence in that case was deliberately covered up,
有一點相當可疑 那樁案子的證據被人刻意湮滅
Could you live a life like that?
你過得了那樣的人生嗎？
Thank you for your cooperation.
多謝協助
That's the last time.
下不為例
Akamine, isn't it time soon?
赤峰，你也差不多了吧？
Right.
是的
Mister!
哥哥！
Minato!
小湊！
Welcome back.
你回來啦
Let's play.
一起玩吧
Sure.
好啊…
May we?
可以嗎？
Yeah. Thanks.
可以，謝謝你
Thank you very much.
衷心感謝你的幫忙
Let's play ball inside.
到家裡玩球吧
We'll play outside.
在外頭玩吧
If we play indoors, the ball might end up behind the doggie again.
進家裡玩球 一不小心又要扔到小狗身上去了
That lady is good at magic tricks.
我跟你說，那個姐姐很會變魔術
Come on, Minato.
小湊，聽著
Last time you mentioned it was…
很會變魔術是…
The witness is just five years old.
證人年僅五歲
Children's memories can be vague.
幼童的記憶模糊不清
His testimony isn't reliable!
可信度不足以佐證！
Excuse me!
不好意思！
Yes?
怎麼了嗎？
I'll go get my ball.
我去拿球
What you mentioned just now,
你剛才所說的
about getting the ball for him.
就是撿球那件事
Did you tell Akizumi about that?
你和我們律師事務所的明墨提過嗎？
Uh, yeah.
這個嘛，是提過
The other day,
就在不久前
he asked me if I've ever been inside the house.
他問我是不是進過社長家
Excuse me.
失陪了
Oof.
嘿咻
I've taken the video.
我都拍清楚了
This is part of an attorney's job, right?
這也是律師的工作吧？
Rest assured, this action doesn't breach any regulations.
不必擔心，你沒有違反條例
I understand that.
話是這麼說沒錯啦
Do you always do this kind of thing?
你總是做這種事？
Excuse me.
我先離開了
Hey.
喂？
Are you free now?
現在方便接電話嗎？
I just got some leashes.
我剛剛買了牽繩
The old one is getting worn out, right?
之前用的不是很舊嗎？
So, I bought new ones.
所以我買了條新的
But I couldn't decide on the color.
但我就是想不出要買哪種顏色
Which do you think would suit Mill better? You choose.
你覺得哪一條適合米魯？ 選一條比較好看的
Go with whichever you like.
選你喜歡的就好
Oh, please!
怎麼這樣？
Fine. I'll get back to you later.
好啦，晚點再打給你
I'm still working.
我還在上班呢
Right, sorry. I'll text you later.
對喔，抱歉，我晚點再傳訊息給你
Bye.
晚點聊
You dropped this.
你東西掉囉
I've been following him for a while,
我一直盯著他
but besides the fact that he's into gambling and drinking,
除了好賭嗜酒以外
I didn't notice anything odd.
他沒有做出其他可疑之舉
Huh?
什麼？
Check this out.
你來看
He's borrowing a total of 1.5 million yen from consumer finance.
他向高利貸借了總共150萬圓
That implies he's spending that much on gambling.
這代表他花在賭博上的錢有這麼多啊
How did you find that out?
但你怎麼得到那消息的？
You want to know?
你確定要問？
Yikes…
真嚇人
He was borrowing money from the victim, Mr. Hanegi, too.
還有一點，他其實也向羽木社長 這位被害人借了錢
How much?
借了多少？
About 300,000 yen.
大概30萬圓
One of the employees witnessed Mr. Hanegi shouting, "Give back my money!"
聽說有員工聽見社長怒喊，要他還錢
In other words, Mr. Ogata was quarreling with the victim over money.
所以說尾形先生和被害人 有過金錢上的糾紛
You know, it's been bothering me.
有一件事我總放不下
Mr. Ogata always wears glasses when he's out.
尾形先生每次外出一定會戴眼鏡
How could he forget them that night?
唯獨案發當晚忘了戴
Did he really just go back for his glasses?
他真的只是去拿眼鏡嗎？
What if it was actually Mr. Ogata who…
該不會是尾形先生殺了羽木社長…
Akamine.
赤峰
Yes?
是
Let's bet on the next race.
在下回賽馬上賭一把吧
Go!
跑啊…
We picked the wrong one!
沒押中！
Trio, 5th, 8th, 15th!
單式投注買了5號、8號、15號！
If only 5th and 15th were swapped, we'd have hit it!
要是把5號跟15號反過來就中了！
No beginner's luck, huh?
就不該碰自己不熟悉的東西
Let's tear this up!
乾脆撕掉算了！
Wait a minute!
等一下！
Huh? Mr. Prosecutor?
什麼？是那個檢察官？
Oh.
是你啊
You won, you know.
你押中了啦！
Huh?
什麼？
This is a trio.
你買的是單式投注
The order doesn't matter.
這種不看押注次序
If all these numbers place in the top three, you win!
只要這些數字出現在前三就中獎了！
Really?
這樣啊？
You won 300,000!
你們中了30萬圓！
That's amazing.
還真是中大獎了
What's going on?
這是怎樣？
This isn't a coincidence, is it?
這不會是巧合吧？
I forgot to ask you something the other day.
前陣子忘了問你一個問題
Give me a break.
拜託你們收斂點
You've won 100,000.
回答了，10萬圓就歸你囉
Huh?
啥？
If you hadn't intervened,
要不是有你制止
we would've tossed away 300,000 yen.
我差點就把30萬圓扔了
You deserve at least 100,000 yen.
你起碼有權收下10萬圓
What do you say? How about we grab drinks?
怎麼樣？要不要去喝個痛快？
The drinks are on us, of course.
酒錢自然也是我出
Let's call it a day soon.
差不多該回家了
Thank you.
好，謝謝
No way we newbies could've known what trios mean.
什麼單式投注？ 我們這種外行人根本不懂
Are you sure I can take this cash?
我真的能收下這筆錢嗎？
Absolutely.
可以啦，來
Here.
喝酒吧
What sort of jobs have you had, Mr. Ogata?
尾形先生之前都從事什麼工作？
What's this all of a sudden?
突然問起這個做什麼？
I'm just curious.
只是好奇
I've worked at a bar, a karaoke joint, traffic control…
我在居酒屋、卡拉OK工作過 還當過交通引導人員
I've done a bunch of stuff.
總之不少就對了
Dammit.
讓人火大
They all fired me, saying I was useless.
所有人都拿我是廢物當理由把我炒了
They all looked down on me.
他們都看不起我，沒有一個人例外
Is that so?
原來如此
Do you think your current job will last?
你現在這份工作能做長久嗎？
Excuse me. Here's your order.
不好意思，啤酒和烤雞肉串來囉
Thank you.
謝謝
You really are nearsighted.
你果真有近視
That's why you took them off at work.
難怪工作時要拿下來
Your job did seem to demand precision.
你的工作似乎還挺繁瑣的
And you happened to forget your glasses on the day of the incident.
你在案發當天忘了帶走眼鏡
Come on, drink up.
來，你也喝一杯
Thanks.
謝謝
Sorry. Let's stop talking about the incident.
抱歉，我看還是不聊案子了
When did you start getting into races?
你喜歡賽馬多久了？
Any thoughts on which horse might perform well next week?
下週的比賽是哪匹馬有望獲勝？
Let's stop talking about work. It puts a damper on the drink.
別再聊工作上的事了 酒都變得難以下嚥
You're right.
說得也是
So, do you say stuff like,
是這麼說的嗎？
"Objection!
“有異議！”
The defense counsel is leading the witness with their questioning."
你們會指責辯方 然後說“剛才那是誘導詰問”？
No.
不
I don't.
我不會說那種話
I'm the one who receives those accusations.
都是別人對我說
Huh?
什麼？
I forgot to introduce myself.
抱歉沒及時說清楚
I'm defending Mr. Keita Hiyama.
我是緋山啓太先生的辯護人
I'm Akizumi.
敝姓明墨
Defending?
辯護人？
You're not a prosecutor?
你不是檢察官？
No.
不是
I see.
我知道了
You guys made me drink and buttered me up to win me over to your side.
你們想藉著請我喝酒、討好我
Attorneys sure use dirty tricks.
律師的手段真下作
But I'm still going to testify
但我會正式作證
that it was Hiyama who did it.
人就是緋山殺的
I don't mind.
沒關係
However, please keep today's events between us.
不過麻煩你別把今天的事說出去
Huh?
什麼？
I gave money to you, a witness,
對目擊證人授予錢財
and even treated you to drinks.
再加上請客
I could be accused of witness interest extortion.
可能會觸犯證人利益勒索罪
And, naturally, you'd be just as guilty for accepting them.
而收取好處的你當然會以同罪論處
Unless,
還是說…
you'd like to return the money I just gave you.
你願意歸還剛才給你的那筆錢？
F-Fine.
我知道了啦
I'll keep quiet about this.
我不會把今天的事說出去
Wonderful.
那就好
There's no such law.
法律上根本沒有那項條例
Ignorance can be dangerous, can't it?
無知真可怕啊
But you knew and didn't tell him.
但你明知沒有這條法律 卻沒有告訴他
You're just as guilty as me.
我們是一丘之貉
I just want to uncover the truth.
我只是想知道真相
Well, see you tomorrow in court.
那我們明天法庭見
Good evening.
你好
All rise.
全體起立
THE SECOND PUBLIC TRIAL
（第二次公審）
Mr. Ogata,
尾形先生
on the day of the incident,
你在案發當天
you realized you had forgotten something and returned to the factory, correct?
發現有東西忘了帶 因而回到工廠，是吧？
Yes.
沒錯
I had left my glasses behind and went back for them.
我忘了拿眼鏡，所以回去拿
I assumed the factory would be closed,
我以為工廠關著
but the lights were still on.
結果燈還亮著
And there, I overheard an argument between Mr. Hanegi and Mr. Hiyama.
我在廠內聽見 羽木社長跟緋山先生在爭吵
Please, let me go home already.
拜託你，今天就讓我下班吧
Sure thing.
可以啊
Once you've finished what I asked, then you can leave.
把我剛才吩咐的做完就能回家
Don't make me repeat myself.
我說過好幾次了
But making one takes quite a bit of time.
這種零件做一個就得耗費不少時間
What?
搞什麼？
Are you really talking back?
你還頂嘴？
You're worthless to society,
我可是出於一片善心才會僱用
and I'm only hiring you out of kindness.
你這種對社會毫無用處的傢伙
Is this how you were raised?
是家庭教育出了問題嗎？
Did your parents not teach you anything?
你爸媽怎麼教你的？
Bring your mom, and I'll give her a talking-to!
下次帶你媽來，我來教育她！
Oh, she died, didn't she?
對喔，你媽死了吧？
I figured it would be a hassle if they found me,
我心裡只覺得被發現就麻煩了
so I decided to stay still until the boss left.
便打算在社長離開前待著不動
I'll kill him.
我要殺了你
After a while,
我等了一會兒
the two left.
見他們兩個紛紛離開
So I tried to leave discreetly.
正想著偷偷摸摸回家去
Then, I heard a scream from the boss' residence.
社長住家那頭傳來一陣慘叫
And when I went to check it out…
我聽見後便過去查看情況…
My apologies for bringing up the distressing memories.
抱歉讓你回想起不愉快的回憶
Everyone,
各位
the security camera inside the factory shows
查看工廠內部的監視器影像
Mr. Ogata entering the premises at around 9:45 p.m.
同樣能看見尾形先生 於晚間9點45分進入工廠的身影
This testimony presents compelling evidence
他的證詞可說是關鍵
that the accused was present at the scene and murdered the victim.
證明了被告人在現場 並且殺害了被害人
That is all.
我方詰問結束
Now, defense counsel, commence the cross-examination.
現在請辯護人進行反詰問
I'm Akizumi, representing the defense. I have a few questions.
我是辯方的明墨，想請教你幾個問題
Mr. Ogata, you overheard
尾形先生，我記得你聲稱
an argument between the victim and the accused at the factory, correct?
自己在工廠內聽見 被告跟被害人起口角，是吧？
Yeah.
對
I mean, yes.
我是說，是的
Did the victim truly utter the words "I'll kill him"?
被告最後真的說了“我要殺了你”？
Yes.
是的
I see.
這樣啊
Very well.
我明白了
Your Honor,
庭上
I request permission to conduct an ex officio inspection.
我希望即刻 以職權進行驗證，可以嗎？
What type of inspection?
你想做什麼樣的驗證？
And is it crucial to the proceedings of this trial?
這項驗證行為對進行本次審理 是必要的嗎？
Yes, Your Honor.
是的
This inspection will provide the crucial material
這項驗證材料至關重要
necessary to establish the uncertainty of Mr. Ogata's testimony.
能證明尾形先生的證詞並不確實
Prosecutor,
檢察官
may he proceed?
你同意嗎？
Well then,
好了
please listen carefully.
請你仔細聆聽
Please, let me go home already.
拜託你，今天就讓我下班吧
Sure thing.
可以啊
Once you've finished what I asked, then you can leave.
把我剛才吩咐的做完就能回家
Don't make me repeat myself.
我說過好幾次了
Right,
是
but I've already finished.
但我全都做完了
What?
什麼？
You've already made the part?
所有零件都完成了？
Impressive.
你還真有一套
All right, you can go home.
好吧，你可以走了
Pause there.
在這裡暫停
Mr. Ogata,
尾形先生
this reconstructed dialogue reflects the ambiance
這段錄音是參考你的證詞
of the interaction between the victim and the accused, based on your testimony.
模擬了被害人與被告 交談的環境錄製而成的
In this audio,
在這段音檔
what did the man at the end say?
最後那名男性說了什麼話？
He said, "Don't leave until you finish making the part."
他說“沒把零件做完不准走”
Mr. Ogata, I'll ask you another question.
我再問你一次，尾形先生
What was the tone of voice used by this man?
那名男性是用什麼語氣 說出這句話的？
He gave an order in a commanding manner.
用脅迫性的語氣說“給我去做零件”
Did he say, "You can go home"?
“你可以走了”這句話呢？
H-He never said that.
他沒說那句
Do you confirm that the conversation
你聽見的被告與被害人之間的 實際對話內容
between the accused and the victim that you heard was akin to this audio?
和這段錄音的內容相同，是嗎？
Y…
沒…
Y-Yes.
沒錯
We intentionally integrated machinery noise into this audio
為了刻意模擬現場環境
to replicate the ambiance of the factory.
這段錄音裡加入了 工廠內的機台運作聲
Next, please listen to this audio clip
接下來請仔細聆聽去除機台噪音後的
without the machinery noise.
純對話音檔
Please, let me go home already.
拜託你，今天就讓我下班吧
Sure thing.
可以啊
Once you've finished what I asked, then you can leave.
把我剛才吩咐的做完就能回家
Don't make me repeat myself.
我說過好幾次了
Right,
是
but I've already finished.
但我全都做完了
What?
什麼？
You've already made the part?
所有零件都完成了？
Impressive.
你還真有一套
All right, you can go home.
好吧，你可以走了
Mr. Ogata, I'll inquire once more.
我再問你一次，尾形先生
At the time of the incident,
案發當時
was Mr. Hanegi shouting at Mr. Hiyama, just like in this audio?
羽木社長如這份音檔 朝著緋山先生不斷怒罵嗎？
Uh…
那個…
Did you truly hear an argument between the accused and the victim?
你是真的聽見了 被害人與被告的爭執嗎？
Is it possible that you couldn't discern their conversation amidst the noise?
身處這樣的雜音之中 你應該無法理解對話內容吧？
No…
不…
And are you sure about forgetting your glasses?
再說，你的目的真的是眼鏡嗎？
Perhaps, to conceal the true motive behind your return to the factory,
你為了掩飾自己回到工廠的真正原因
you and the prosecution fabricated the story of retrieving your glasses.
和檢察官商量後 姑且決定以拿眼鏡作為藉口
But, in reality, you went back for something else entirely.
但你真正的目的應該不是眼鏡吧？
Let's see, for instance…
我想想，可能是…
a hearing aid.
助聽器之類的
Objection!
有異議！
That is mere speculation by the defense!
剛才的問題不過是辯方的主觀臆測！
APD,
APD
Auditory Processing Disorder.
你罹患的疾病
It's the condition you have.
名為“聽覺處理障礙”
While it may not significantly impact comprehension of everyday conversations,
症狀在日常生活對話上通常不成問題
in noisy and bustling environments,
但處在喧鬧或紛亂的場合裡
voices may become muffled and comprehension may be challenging.
便會出現人聲模糊化 或無法理解對話內容的情況
It seems you like races,
你似乎熱愛賽馬
yet even at the racetrack,
人在賽馬場時
you always listen to radio commentary through earphones.
你總會戴上耳機聽收音機，沒錯吧？
They rent out radios to individuals with visual or hearing impairments.
那是賽馬場專門出借給
The racetrack is always bustling and noisy, after all.
畢竟場內一向熱鬧且嘈雜
I have questioned the neighbors about the circumstances of the incident.
我們向附近居民 瞭解了案發當時的情況
They reported hearing the sounds of machinery late into the night.
他們表示案發當天深夜 還聽得見工廠傳來的機台聲響
The machine Mr. Hiyama was using is used for shaving metal pieces
緋山先生操作的機台專門切割金屬片
and produces considerable noise.
造成的噪音並不小
To clarify the witness' statement,
為了釐清證人的供詞
I request to play the audio, marked as evidence number 38,
我方申請出示 辯方請求證據第38號的音檔
as requested by the defense counsel.
讓證人聆聽
This recording captures the ambient noises of the factory under similar conditions.
這是在相同條件下錄製而成的 純工廠內部聲響
Very well.
我明白了
Proceed.
播放吧
Mr. Ogata, you maintain
尾形先生，我想問你
that even amidst this machinery noise,
身處這種機台噪音之中
you could accurately discern the contents of the conversation.
你還能聽清楚
Is that correct?
正確的對話內容？
W-Well…
那是因為…
You've changed jobs frequently due to this condition.
你因為聽力障礙 而換了不少工作，對吧？
No matter what job you got,
不管從事何種職業
you were dismissed because of your hearing.
都因為耳朵的問題慘遭開除
It must have been hard.
你一定很煎熬
You can't keep mistaking orders like this.
你犯下這種錯，我們也不好做啊
It must've been painful.
一定很痛苦
Mr. Ogata, you can't keep doing this.
尾形先生，別給我添麻煩啦
It must've seemed unfair.
一定無法接受
I offer my sympathies.
我能理解
You!
你這混蛋！
This isn't what we discussed!
這跟我們說好的不一樣！
This is why I didn't want to do this!
我當初就拒絕了！
Screw you! You bastard!
-喂，你就是個混帳！ -別衝動！
-Hey! -I order the witness to leave!
-喂！ -在此命令證人退庭！
Hey!
喂，檢察官，你是個混蛋！
Order in the court!
全體肅靜！
The court will adjourn for the time being.
本庭暫且休庭
Prosecutor.
檢座
You're not surprised.
你看起來一點都不驚訝
But that's expected.
這是當然的
There's no way you would be unaware of the witness' condition.
檢座不可能不清楚證人的病情
If it were to become known,
若讓人得知證人耳朵有異狀
it would undermine the credibility of his testimony.
會動搖證詞的可信度
You told Mr. Ogata,
你給過尾形先生
"I'll handle this discreetly so your condition remains hidden.
“我會好好安排 絕對不會曝光你的病情
Just testify as instructed."
請你按指示作證”
Isn't that right?
這樣的承諾吧？
It was an impressive statement indeed.
他的供詞是真的相當出色
Hey!
喂！
Did you approach me only to learn about my hearing impairment?
-尾形先生！ -你接近我
Will you even expose my condition just so you can win?
你為了勝訴不惜暴露別人的病情？
That's why I invited you to that place.
所以我才會邀你去那家店啊
Sorry. Let's stop talking about the incident.
抱歉，我看還是不聊案子了
When did you start getting into races?
你喜歡賽馬多久了？
Any thoughts on which horse might perform well next week?
下週的比賽是哪匹馬有望獲勝？
Let's stop talking about work. It puts a damper on the drink.
別再聊工作上的事了 酒都變得難以下嚥
Amidst the noise of the trains,
我就是想確認一下
I wanted to see if you could discern my words.
你在電車的運行聲中 能否聽清我說的話
What grudge do you have against me?
你跟我是有什麼仇？
Hiyama killed the boss.
緋山殺了社長！
He's a criminal! A killer!
那傢伙是罪犯！是殺人犯！
My apologies.
很抱歉
I'm driven to win, even if it means revealing someone's disorder.
我不惜暴露他人的病情也想勝訴
It's simply part of my job.
那就是我的工作
Screw you!
別鬧了！
Hey!
喂！
I might lose my job again!
我可能會因為這件事再度失業！
You want me to die, is that it?!
你是要我去死嗎？
Do you want to die?
你想死嗎？
Whether you live or die is none of my concern.
我不在乎你的人生會如何
I'll exploit anything, even a person's disability.
無論是有障礙或其他理由 我都會利用
As long as your account of hearing their conversation remains unclear,
若“你聽見兩人對話”的證詞不明確
I'll stop at nothing to prove that.
我會不擇手段證明此事
I'll go to any lengths to serve my client's interests.
我會竭盡全力維護客戶的利益
That's what attorneys do.
那正是律師的職責
I have only spoken the truth.
若是因為說出真話
You have no grounds to resent me. Goodbye.
而蒙受怨恨倒讓人傷腦筋，再會
Nevertheless,
不過呢
consider this a form of reparation.
雖然算不上補償
Dismissing someone due to a condition that doesn't impact business operations
假使病情不影響業務
If you pursue legal action against every company that dismissed you,
若是將以往開除你的公司 全數告上法院
you could probably…
你或許…
win 10 million at least.
可以贏得一千萬圓的賠償
Since we've shared drinks together, I'll handle this case at no cost, anytime.
我們是喝過酒的朋友 我隨時願意無償為你效勞
Consider it.
如果你願意的話
It may seem unusual coming from me,
這話讓我來說稍嫌諷刺
but you should never forgive those who discriminate against you
但絕對不能放過那些
because of your disability.
以身體障礙為由區別對待的人
Goodbye.
告辭
Stay in line.
不要亂了隊形喔
-Hello.
-你好
Mr. Akizumi says he'll return after making a call.
律師說他要打通電話再回來
Hmm.
這樣啊
He's probably calling his daughter.
反正是打給他女兒吧
Saya, was it?
是叫紗耶來著？
Huh?
什麼？
SAYA HAS SENT A PHOTO
（紗耶傳送了照片）
How do you like the leash?
牽繩看起來挺好看的
Hey, I want to take a picture.
你慢一點，小豆，我想拍照
Mame, look this way.
小豆，看這邊
Hey.
喂
Stop that.
別鬧了
I'm trying to take a picture!
我在拍照啦
MASAKI AKIZUMI
（明墨正樹）
Okay, let's have Class 2 go first.
從二班開始進去
-Hello!
-大家好！
You're so full of energy.
真有活力
A prosecutor's job is…
檢察官的工作
to teach people that it's important to say sorry when they do something wrong.
是讓罪犯明白道歉的重要性 這是我們的職責
Why?
為什麼？
Tell us.
告訴我們嘛
I bet your mommy and daddy tell you that too.
你們的父母也會告誡你們吧
If you do something wrong, you have to feel sorry for it
當你們做錯事時 他們會說“好好反省”
and never do it again.
還有“下次不准再犯”
Oh? Don't they tell you that?
對不對？
-Yeah! -They do!
-對！ -他們會說！
But the thing is,
但是啊
it's human nature to make mistakes.
人類有時會犯下罪行
So we help people who have done wrong
我們檢察官要為那些犯罪的人
by giving them time to reflect on their wrongdoing.
創造時間讓他們正視自己做出的惡事
What do you think happens to them?
這麼一來，你們覺得他們會怎麼樣？
They become better people.
會變成好人
-Better people!
-會變好人！
I really hope so!
能那樣是最好的！
Japan is a country
在日本這個國家
where even people who've made mistakes can make a fresh start.
即便是犯了罪的人也能夠重新做人
Do you believe that?
你真心如此認為嗎？
Consider this.
你仔細想想
Think about it.
請各位也仔細想想
After someone who did something wrong leaves prison,
一個犯了罪的人在出獄後
how can they find a place for themselves in the world?
要如何找到自己的歸屬？
How can they find happiness?
要如何找到自己的幸福？
They can never find happiness.
罪犯永遠得不到幸福
Eventually, they succumb to despair, kill again, or end their own lives.
最終會在絕望之下再度殺人 或者自絕性命
It's the only future that awaits them.
那就是等著罪犯的未來
The instant you become a murderer, your life is over.
在成為殺人犯的那一刻 你的人生就毀了
It can't be helped. After all…
這也沒辦法，畢竟啊…
you've committed murder.
你奪走了別人的性命
The court is back in session.
庭審重啟
Your Honor,
庭上
we would like to request an investigation into new evidence.
我方申請查證新證據
New evidence?
新證據？
What kind of evidence?
是哪種證據？
We've been searching for this for a long time.
這是本案中一直找不到的
It's the murder weapon.
凶器
Defense counsel, could you please confirm?
辯護人，請你確認一下
Please confirm.
請檢查一下
What's the plan now?
之後該怎麼辦？
There's no need to worry.
沒什麼好慌的
Carry on as usual.
請你保持平常心
But that hammer is mine--
但那支鐵鎚是我的…
Mr. Hiyama,
緋山先生
try to remember.
請你好好回想一下
Before the incident,
你在案發之前
did you happen to misplace the hammer?
是不是在哪弄丟了那把鐵鎚？
NEXT EPISODE: THE VERDICT IS DELIVERED!
（赤峰親眼所見的驚人真相為何？）
We're doing all this to prove your innocence.
為了證明你的清白 我們正在努力奔走
I'll show you how to win a trial.
我會讓你見識到所謂的勝訴方法